how does a vegan or vegetarian diet
affect bone density and what other
factors contribute watch the video to
find out
[Music]
osteoporosis is estimated to affect 200
million people worldwide
literally meaning porous bone
osteoporosis is a disease characterized
by reduced bone formation excessive bone
loss or combination of both leading to
bone fragility and increased risk of
fractures and bone mineral density is
the most robust and consistent predictor
of osteoporotic fracture
what can we eat
to boost our bone density well we know
that increasing consumption of plant
foods is associated with increased bone
mineral density there's an extensive
range of micronutrients and
phytochemicals packaged within plants
that can be powerful promoters of bone
health so healthcare professionals
should be encouraged to advise the
increased consumption of plant-based
foods particularly in mid-life
irrespective of the client's underlying
dietary pattern meaning no matter how
much meat or junk they eat adding more
healthy plant foods may help prevent the
development of osteoporosis on the other
hand a more animal source nutrient
pattern has been associated with a
higher risk of fractures suggesting that
a more animal-based diet is related to
bone fragility someone would expect less
osteoporosis in those eating plant-based
diets but you don't know
until you put it to the test
the incidence of osteoporosis in
vegetarians and omnivores the first
study published nearly 50 years ago and
the density of the bones that were
measured was significantly greater in
the vegetarians than the omnivores in
fact the average bone densities the
vegetarians in their 70s was greater
than the densities of the meat eaters in
their 50s bottom line these results
suggest there's less likelihood of
vegetarians developing osteoporosis in
old age
turns out though that the researchers
screwed up dexa scanning which is what
we use now didn't come online until the
1980s so the researchers were just using
just regular x-rays and they confused
the readings such that darker bones on
the x-ray got a higher score but that
actually means less bone so their
conclusion should have been the opposite
of what they claimed so vegetarians had
worse bone mineral density
fast forward about 40 years by which
time nine studies have been done on
thousands of individuals and all in all
the results suggest that vegetarian
diets particularly vegan diets are
associated with lower bone mineral
density but the magnitude of the
association is clinically insignificant
meaning the difference was so small as
to not really matter out in the real
world reinforcing the fact that
vegetarian diets have no clinically
detrimental effect on bone health
and it's important to note that the
findings of lower bone mineral density
didn't fully control for key confounding
factors such as for differences in body
weight we know that people who are obese
have stronger bones why
because their weight lifting 50 pounds
all day every day and maybe a hundred
pounds if you walk around with a hundred
pound backpack every day your bones
would grow stronger too that's how you
build strong bones weight-bearing
exercise so people who weigh more have
denser bones and vegetarians especially
vegans have such low rates of obesity
that no wonder on average they would
have lower bone density the researchers
didn't take weight into account but if
the difference they found isn't even
clinically significant who cares as of
2009 the answer to the question is
vegetarianism a serious risk factor for
osteoporotic fracture the answer was no
vegetarianism is not a serious risk
factor
by 2018 the latest meta-analysis on
veganism vegetarianism and bone mineral
density we're up to 20 studies involving
tens of thousands of participants and
again
lower bone mineral density was found in
studies of vegetarians and vegans
compared to meat-eaters the researchers
conclude that vegetarian and vegan diets
need to be appropriately planned to
preserve their bones but wait did they
account for the obesity thing
no they did not they just used what are
called crude risk ratios meaning no
adjustments for confounding factors like
weight so they didn't control for things
like age smoking obesity exercise and so
the results are really uninterpretable
but no one had gone through the trouble
of going back through all those studies
and making the proper adjustments until
now
the title gives it away differences in
bone mineral density between vegetarians
and non-vegetarians become marginal when
accounting for differences in body size
factors yes bone mineral density values
were significantly lower among
vegetarians than among non-vegetarians
just like is the case with nearly every
study on bone mineral density and excess
body weight but forget clinical
significance these differences even lost
statistical significance upon adjustment
for body size factors suggesting that
lower bone mass among vegetarians is in
larger parts explained by their lower
bmi and waist circumference thus it's
not so much the composition of the diets
of vegetarians and vegans as much as it
is the fact that they become so much
slimmer
now a small but statistically
significant difference remained for
total lower spine density a difference
of 0.03
this was dismissed as having little
clinical relevance but is that true if
you look at the reproducibility of bone
mineral density measurements in daily
medical practice you can see how if you
repeat tests back to back there's some
scatter in the measurements and so a
significant difference really has to be
more than the inherent variation and
indeed
expressed as the smallest detected
difference you really need a bone mental
density disparity of at least 0.05
at the spine before it can be considered
a significant change and so indeed there
does appear to be little clinical
relevance
however even if vegetarians and vegans
basically have the same bone density at
the same weight
everyone who is skinny is at risk low
bmi is a risk factor for fracture so all
persons in a low body weight category
consuming any kind of diet should be
monitored for osteoporosis
[Music]
you